The will to live life differently can start
الرغبة للعيش بشكل مختلف يمكن أن تبدأ
in some of the most unusual places.
في أحد الأماكن الغير عادية.
This is where I come from, Todmorden.
أتيت من هنا ، " تدموردن ".
It's a market town in the north of England,
إنها مدينة تسوق في شمال انكلترا .
15,000 people, between Leeds and Manchester,
يقطنها 15 ألف شخص ، بين ليدز ومانشستر ،
fairly normal market town.
قرية تسوق عادية.
It used to look like this,
كانت تبدوا هكذا،
and now it's more like this,
والآن تبدو هكذا،
with fruit and veg and herbs sprouting up all over the place.
فواكه وخضار وأعشاب تنتشر في جميع أرجاء المكان.
We call it propaganda gardening. (Laughter)
نحن نسميها دعاية التشجير.(ضحك)
Corner row railway, station car park,
في وسط سكة الحديد ، كراج سيارات المحطة،
front of a health center, people's front gardens,
أمام مركز الصحة ، أمام الحدائق الخاصة،
and even in front of the police station. (Laughter)
وحتى أمام مخفر الشرطة. (ضحك)
We've got edible canal towpaths,
لدينا ممرات لسحب القوارب قابلة للأكل ،
and we've got sprouting cemeteries.
ولدينا مقابر ذات براعم .
The soil is extremely good. (Laughter)
التربة فيها جيدة للغاية.(ضحك)
We've even invented a new form of tourism.
لقد اخترعنا نوعاً جديداً للسياحة.
It's called vegetable tourism, and believe it or not,
تسمى سياحة الخضراوات، صدقوا أو لا تصدقوا ،
people come from all over the world to poke around in our raised beds,
يأتي الناس من كل مكان في العالم يدفعهم الفضول لرؤية أسرتنا الزراعية المرتفعة،
even when there's not much growing. (Laughter)
حتى عندما لا تكون قد نمت كثيراً.(ضحك)
But it starts a conversation. (Laughter)
ولكنها تشعل النقاش.(ضحك)
And, you know, we're not doing it because we're bored. (Laughter)
وكما تعرفون نحن لا نفعل ذلك لأننا نشعر بالملل
We're doing it because we want to start a revolution.
نحن نفعل ذلك لأننا نريد إحداث ثورة .
We tried to answer this simple question:
حاولنا الإجابة عن هذا السؤال البسيط :
Can you find a unifying language that cuts across age
هل يمكننا إيجاد لغة موحدة تتقاطع مع العصر
and income and culture that will help people themselves
وإيرادات وثقافة بإمكانها مساعدة الناس لكي
find a new way of living,
يجدوا طريقة جديدة للعيش ،
see spaces around them differently,
يشاهدوا ما يحيط بهم بشكل مختلف،
think about the resources they use differently,
يفكروا باستخدام الثروات بشكل مختلف ،
interact differently?
و يتفاعلو بشكل مختلف ؟
Can we find that language?
هل يمكننا إيجاد تلك اللغة ؟
And then, can we replicate those actions?
ومن ثم ، هل يمكننا تكرار تلك الأعمال ؟
And the answer would appear to be yes,
والإجابة يجب أن تكون نعم ،
and the language would appear to be food.
واللغة يجب أن تكون الطعام .
So, three and a half years ago, a few of us
جلس البعض منا ،منذ ثلاث سنوات ونصف،
sat around a kitchen table and
على طاولة المطبخ
we just invented the whole thing. (Laughter)
واخترعنا كل شيء. (ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We came up with a really simple game plan that we put to a public meeting.
لقد جئنا بمخطط للعب بسيطة جداً وناقشناه في اجتماع عام.
We did not consult. We did not write a report.
لم نتشاور. و لم نكتب تقارير.
Enough of all that. (Laughter)
يكفي ذلك (ضحك)
And we said to that public meeting in Todmorden,
وقلنا في ذلك الاجتماع العام في تدموردن،
look, let's imagine that our town
انظروا ، دعونا نتخيل أن مدينتنا
is focused around three plates:
ترتكز حول ثلاث أطباق:
a community plate, the way we live our everyday lives;
طبق المجتمع - الطريقة التي نعيش بها حياتنا اليومية؛
a learning plate, what we teach our kids in school
طبق التعلم - ماذا نعلم أطفالنا في المدرسة
and what new skills we share amongst ourselves;
وما الخبرات الجديد التي نتشاركها مع أنفسنا؛
and business, what we do with the pound in our pocket
وطبق العمل - ماذا نفعل مع المال في جيوبنا
and which businesses we choose to support.
وما العمل الذي نختار دعمه.
Now, let's imagine those plates agitated
الآن، لنتخيل هذه الأطباق تتحرك مع
with community actions around food.
أعمال المجتمع بخصوص الطعام .
If we start one of those community plates spinning,
إذا بدأنا بغزل واحد من أطباق المجتمع تلك،
that's really great, that really starts to empower people,
فإن ذلك سيكون عظيم حقا، إذ سيبدأ باستثمار طاقات الناس،
but if we can then spin that community plate
ولكن إذا استطعنا غزل طبق الجمهور
with the learning plate, and then spin it with the business plate,
مع طبق التعليم، ومن ثم مع طبق التجارة،
we've got a real show there, we've got some action theater.
أصبح لدينا عرض حقيقي هناك، أصبحنا نملك مسرح عمل.
We're starting to build resilience ourselves.
بدأنا ببناء مرونتنا بأنفسنا.
We're starting to reinvent community ourselves,
بدأنا بإعادة تكوين المجتمع بأنفسنا،
and we've done it all without a flipping strategy document.
وفعلنا ذلك دون مستندات للاستراتيجية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And here's the thing as well.
وفي مايلي الشيء الأهم.
We've not asked anybody's permission to do this,
نحن لم نطلب إذن أحد لنفعل هذا
we're just doing it. (Laughter)
نحن فقط نفعله. (ضحك)
And we are certainly not waiting for that check
ونحن بالتأكيد لا ننتظر ذلك الشيك
to drop through the letterbox before we start,
ليأتي عبر صندوق الرسائل قبل أن نبدأ،
and most importantly of all, we are not daunted
والأكثر أهمية من كل شيء ، نحن لسنا متخوفون
by the sophisticated arguments that say,
من النقاشات المعقدة التي تقول:
"These small actions are meaningless in the face of tomorrow's problems,"
"هذه الأعمال الصغيرة لا معنى لها في مواجهة مشاكل الغد"
because I have seen the power of small actions,
لأني رأيت طاقة الأعمال الصغيرة،
and it is awesome.
إنها رائعة.
So, back to the public meeting. (Laughter)
لنعود للاجتماع العام. (ضحك)
We put that proposition to the meeting, two seconds,
وضعنا ذلك الاقتراح في الاجتماع،
and then the room exploded.
ثانيتين وانفجرت القاعة بالنقاش.
I have never, ever experienced anything like that in my life.
لم ولن أرى شيء مثل ذلك في حياتي.
And it's been the same in every single room, in every town
و تكرّر هذا في كلّ غرفة، في كلّ مدينة
that we've ever told our story.
ذكرنا فيها قصتنا.
People are ready and respond to the story of food.
الناس مستعدّون و استجابو لقصة الأكل.
They want positive actions they can engage in,
يريدون سلوك إيجابي ليجذبهم،
and in their bones, they know it's time
و في عظامهم، هم يعلمون انه الوقت المناسب
to take personal responsibility
لاتخاذ مسئولية شخصية
and invest in more kindness to each other
و استثمار اللطف فيما بيننا
and to the environment.
و مع البيئة.
And since we had that meeting three and a half years ago,
ومنذ ذلك الاجتماع قبل ثلاث سنوات و نصف،
it's been a heck of a roller coaster.
كانت تلك المدة مثل قطار الملاهي السريع.
We started with a seed swap, really simple stuff,
بدأنا تبادل البذور، أشياء بسيطة جداً،
and then we took an area of land, a strip on the side
ثم أخذنا مساحة من الأرض، قطاع على جانب
of our main road, which was a dog toilet, basically,
شارعنا العام، عبارة عن حمام للكلاب،سابقا،
and we turned it into a really lovely herb garden.
ثم حولناها إلى حديقة جميلة مليئة بالعشب.
We took the corner of the car park in the station
أخذنا زاوية من مواقف السيارات في المحطة
that you saw, and we made vegetable beds
الذي رأيتموه، و زرعنا العديد من الخضروات
for everybody to share and pick from themselves.
للجميع ليتشاركوا ويقطفوا من صنيعهم.
We went to the doctors. We've just had
ذهبنا الى الأطباء، بعد إنشاء
a 6-million-pound health center built in Todmorden,
المركز الصحي مباشرة بقيمة ٦ مليون باوند في 'تودموردن'،
and for some reason that I cannot comprehend,
و لسبب ما لا استطيع فهمه
it has been surrounded by prickly plants. (Laughter)
أحاطت به النباتات الشائكة. (ضحك)
So we went to the doctors, said, "Would you mind us taking them up?"
لذلك ذهبنا الى الأطباء ،وقلنا ' هل تسمحون لنا بإستأصالهم؟'
They said, "Absolutely fine, provided you get planning permission
قالوا، "طبعا، لقد تحصلتم على موافقتنا على التخطيط
and you do it in Latin and you do it in triplicate,"
و باللاتيني و بثلاث نسخ،'
so we did — (Laughter) — and now there are fruit trees
و فعلنا ذلك -(ضحك)- و الآن يوجد أشجار من الفواكه
and bushes and herbs and vegetables
و شجيرات و أعشاب و خضروات
around that doctor's surgery.
حول مكان الجراحة .
And there's been lots of other examples, like the corn
و يوجد العديد من الأمثلة الأخرى، مثل الذرة
that was in front of the police station,
كان ذلك أمام مخفر الشرطة،
and the old people's home that we've planted it with food
ومنازل الناس القديمة التي زرعناها بالأطعمة.
that they can pick and grow.
التي يستطيعون أخذها و زراعتها.
But it isn't just about growing,
لكن الأمر لا يتعلق فقط بالزراعة،
because we all are part of this jigsaw.
لأننا جميعنا جزء من هذه الأحجية.
It's about taking those artistic people in your community
الأمر هو باستثمار أولئك الناس الفنانين في مجتمعنا
and doing some fabulous designs in those raised beds
ليقوموا بعمل تصاميم مذهلة في المزارع
to explain to people what's growing there,
لأخبار الناس الآخرين بماذا يزرع هناك ،
because there's so many people that don't really recognize
لانه يوجد أناس كثيرين لا يلاحظون
a vegetable unless it's in a bit of plastic
الخضروات حتى تكون مغلفة بالبلاستيك
with a bit of an instruction packet on the top. (Laughter)
مع بعض التعليمات في الأعلى. (ضحك)
So we have some people who designed these things,
لدينا بعض الناس الذين يصممون هذه الأشياء،
"If it looks like this, please don't pick it, but if it looks like this,
"اذا كان شكلها هكذا،أرجوك لا تأخذها، لكن اذا كان شكلها هكذا،
help yourself."
ساعد نفسك."
This is about sharing and investing in kindness.
هذا كله عن المشاركة و الاستثمار في اللطف.
And for those people that don't want to do either
و هؤلاء الأشخاص الذين لا يريدون فعل
of those things, maybe they can cook,
اي شيء، ربما يستطيعون الطهو،
so we pick them seasonally and then we go on the street,
نحن نقوم بقطف هذه الأطعمة موسميا ومن ثم نذهب إلى الشارع،
or in the pub, or in the church,
أو الى الحانة، أو الى الكنيسة،
or wherever people are living their lives.
أو إلى أي مكان يعيش فيه الناس.
This is about us going to the people and saying,
نذهب إلى الناس ونقول لهم،
"We are all part of the local food jigsaw,
"نحن جميعنا جزء من أحجية الطعام المحلية،
we are all part of a solution."
نحن جميعنا جزء من الحل."
And then, because we know we've got vegetable tourists
ولأننا نعلم بأن لدينا سياح للخضروات
and we love them to bits and they're absolutely fantastic,
ولأننا نحبهم أن يقضموا و لآنهم رائعون،
we thought, what could we do to give them an even better experience?
فكرنا، ماذا نستطيع ان نفعل لإعطاءهم خبرة افضل؟
So we invented, without asking, of course,
لذلك اخترعنا، من غير ان نسأل بالطبع،
the Incredible Edible Green Route.
الطريق الأخضر الصالح للأكل الذي لا يصدق.
And this is a route of exhibition gardens,
و هذا طريق للمعارض في الحدائق،
and edible towpaths, and bee-friendly sites, and the story
طريق جر المراكب الصالح للأكل، والمواقع صديقة النحل، و قصة
of pollinators, and it's a route that we designed
المُلقِحًات، الطريق الذي صممناه
that takes people through the whole of our town,
والذي يأخذ الناس لزيارة كامل قريتنا،
past our cafes and our small shops, through our market,
عبر المقاهي ومحلاتنا الصغير، خلال أسواقنا،
not just to and fro from the supermarket,
ليس فقط من وإلى السوبرماركت،
and we're hoping that, in changing people's footfall
و نأمل، بذلك أن نغير خطى الناس
around our town, we're also changing their behavior.
حول مدينتنا، ونحن أيضا نغير تصرفاتهم.
And then there's the second plate, the learning plate.
ثم هناك الصحن الثاني و هو صحن التعليم.
Well, we're in partnership with a high school.
في الحقيقة، نحن في شراكة مع مدرسة ثانوية.
We've created a company. We are designing and building
لقد أنشأنا شركة. نحن نصمم و نصنع
an aquaponics unit in some land that was spare
وحدة الأكوافونيك للزراعة في إحدى الأراضي الخالية
at the back of the high school, like you do,
خلف المدرسة الثانوية، كالعادة،
and now we're going to be growing fish and vegetables
و الآن سنستزرع السمك و الخضروات
in an orchard with bees,
في بستان من النحل،
and the kids are helping us build that,
ونحن نقوم ببناءه بمساعدة الأطفال،
and the kids are on the board, and because the community
و الأطفال يشاركون معنا ذلك، وبسبب أن المجتمع
was really keen on working with the high school,
كان حريصا على العمل في المدرسة الثانوية،
the high school is now teaching agriculture,
فإن المدرسة الثانوية الآن تقوم بتدريس الزراعة،
and because it's teaching agriculture, we started to think,
و لانها بدأت بتدريس الزراعة، بدأنا بالتفكير،
how could we then get those kids that never had a qualification
كيف يمكننا ان نعطي هؤلاء الأطفال الذين ليس لديهم أي مؤهل
before in their lives but are really excited about growing,
سابق في حياتهم والمتحمسون للزراعة،
how can we give them some more experience?
كيف يمكننا ان نعطيهم بعضا من الخبرة؟
So we got some land that was donated
حصلنا على بعض الأراضي
by a local garden center.
من مركز الحدائق المحلية.
It was really quite muddy, but in a truly incredible way,
كانت مليئة بالطين، لكن بطريقة عجيبة جدا،
totally voluntary-led, we have turned that
حولنا هذه الحدائق بالعمل الطوعي
into a market garden training center,
الى مركز تدريب حدائق السوق،
and that is polytunnels and raised beds
و هذه أنفاق للزراعة و أسرة مرتفعة زراعية
and all the things you need to get the soil under your fingers
و كل الاشياء التي نحتاجها لوضع التربة على أصابعنا
and think maybe there's a job in this for me in the future.
وكل هذا يحثنا للتفكير بأنه قد أجد عملا لي في هذا المجال في المستقبل.
And because we were doing that, some local academics said,
و لأننا نفعل ذلك، بعض الأكادميين المحليين قالوا لنا،
"You know, we could help design
"على فكرة، نحن نستطيع ان نساعد في تصميم
a commercial horticulture course for you.
دورة في مجال البستنة التجارية لكم.
There's not one that we know of."
على حد علمنا، لا يوجد دورة في هذا المجال "
So they're doing that, and we're going to launch it later this year,
لذلك هم يفعلون هذا ، وسنقوم باطلاقها لاحقا في هذه السنة،
and it's all an experiment, and it's all voluntary.
و كل هذا عبارة عن تجربة،و كله من متطوعين.
And then there's the third plate,
ثم يأتي الطبق الثالث،
because if you walk through an edible landscape,
اذا مشيت بجانب مناظر طبيعية تصلح للأكل،
and if you're learning new skills, and if you start to get
و اذا كنت تتعلم مهارات جديدة، و اذا بدأت
interested in what's growing seasonally,
تتحمس لما ينمو موسميا،
you might just want to spend more of your own money
ربما تريد ان تنفق بعض من مالك الخاص
in support of local producers,
لدعم المنتجين المحليين،
not just veg, but meat and cheese and beer
ليس فقط الخضروات، لكن اللحم و الجبن و البيرة
and whatever else it might be.
و اي شيء آخر.
But then, we're just a community group, you know.
لكننا فقط مجتمع صغير، كما تعلم.
We're just all volunteers. What could we actually do?
جميعنا متطوعون. ماذا بأمكاننا ان نفعل؟
So we did some really simple things.
لذلك فعلنا آشياء بسيطة جداً.
We fundraised, we got some blackboards,
جمعنا العديد من الأموال، و أحضرنا بعض الألواح المدرسية (السبورة)،
we put "Incredible Edible" on the top,
و وضعنا الأصناف 'القابلة للأكل المدهشة' في الأعلى،
we gave it every market trader that was selling locally,
و أعطيناها الى جميع الأسواق التجارية التي تبيع محليا،
and they scribbled on what they were selling in any one week.
و قد خربشوا على ما كانوا يبيعونه في أي أسبوع.
Really popular. People congregated around it.
أصبحت مشهورة. تجمهر الناس حولها.
Sales were up.
ارتفعت المبيعات.
And then, we had a chat with the farmers, and we said,
ثم تحدثنا مع المزارعين، و قلنا،
"We're really serious about this,"
"نحن جادون جداً لهذا الأمر،"
but they didn't actually believe us, so we thought,
لكنهم في الحقيقة لم يصدقوننا، لذلك فكرنا،
okay, what should we do? I know. If we can create
حسنا، ماذا يجب علينا ان نفعل؟ إذا كان بامكاننا أن ننشيء
a campaign around one product and show them
حملة لسلعة واحدة ونريهم
there is local loyalty to that product,
بأن هناك إخلاص محلي للسلعة،
maybe they'll change their mind and see we're serious.
ربما سيغيرون آرائهم ويعلمون أننا جادون.
So we launched a campaign -- because it just amuses me --
لذلك افتتحتا حملة-- لانه يسليني--
called Every Egg Matters. (Laughter)
اسمها "كل بيضة مهمة". (ضحك)
And what we did was we put people on our egg map.
وما فعلناه هو أننا وضعنا الناس في خريطة البيض الخاصة بنا.
It's a stylized map of Togmorden.
أنها خريطة مبسطة لـ'توجموردين'.
Anybody that's selling their excess eggs
أي شخص يبيع بيضه الزائد
at the garden gate, perfectly legally, to their neighbors,
عند بوابة الحديقة، بشكل قانوني، لجيرانه،
we've stuck on there. We started with four,
بدأنا بأربعة،
and we've now got 64 on, and the result of that was
ونحن الآن قد حصلنا على 64، وكانت نتيجة ذلك
that people were then going into shops
أن الناس كانوا يذهبون الى الأسواق
asking for a local Todmorden egg, and the result of that
و يطلبون بيض 'تودموردن' المحلية،
was, some farmers upped the amount of flocks they got
ونتيجة لذلك قام بعض المزارعين بزيادة القطيع الذي لديهم
of free range birds, and then they went on to meat birds,
من الطيور خارج الأقفاص، ومن ثم ذهبوا الى لحوم الطيور،
and although these are really, really small steps,
وعلى الرغم من أن هذه كلها خطوات صغيرة جداً،
that increasing local economic confidence
لزيادة الثقة الاقتصادية المحلية
is starting to play out in a number of ways,
التي بدأت تؤدي أداء جيدا بطرق متعددة،
and we now have farmers doing cheese
حيث أنه لدينا الآن مزارعين يعملون الجبن
and they've upped their flocks and rare breed pigs,
وقد زادوا قطعانهم و سلالات الخنازير النادرة التي لديهم،
they're doing pasties and pies and things
أنهم يعدون فطائر اللحم والشطائر وأشياء
that they would have never done before.
لم يفعلوها من قبل.
We've got increasing market stalls selling local food,
زاد عدد الأكشاك التي تبيع الطعام المحلي،
and in a survey that local students did for us, 49 percent
وفي دراسة استقصائية تبين بأن الطلاب المحليين ساعدونا بـ ٤٩ في المئة
of all food traders in that town said that their bottom line
من مجمل تجارة الطعام في هذه المدينة حيث ارتفع الخط السفلي
had increased because of what we were actually doing.
بسبب ما نفعله.
And we're just volunteers and it's only an experiment.
و نحن فقط متطوعين و هذا كله تجربة فقط.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, none of this is rocket science.
الآن، لا شيء من هذا في صعوبة علم الصواريخ.
It certainly is not clever, and it's not original.
أنها لا تحتاج للذكاء، وليست ابداعا.
But it is joined up, and it is inclusive.
ولكنها متحدة، و شاملة.
This is not a movement for those people
هذه ليست حركة أناس
that are going to sort themselves out anyway.
يريدون أن يتدبروا أنفسهم بأي طريقة.
This is a movement for everyone.
إنه حراك للجميع.
We have a motto: If you eat, you're in. (Laughter)
لدينا شعار: إذا كنت تآكله، فأنت معنا، (ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Across age, across income, across culture.
لكل الأعمار، والمداخيل، والثقافات.
It's been really quite a roller coaster experience,
لقد كانت حقا تجربة شبيهة بتجربة قطار الملاهي الدوار،
but going back to that first question that we asked,
ولكن لنعود الى اول سؤال سألناه،
is it replicable? Yeah. It most certainly is replicable.
هل يمكن تكرارها؟ نعم. ومن المؤكد أنها قابلة للتكرار.
More than 30 towns in England now are spinning
أكثر من 30 مدينة في إنجلترا الآن تغزل
the Incredible Edible plate.
صحن"المزرعة الصالحة للأكل".
Whichever way they want to do it, of their own volition,
أيا كانت الطريقة التي يريدون ان يفعلونها، على حسب رغبتهم الخاصة،
they're trying to make their own lives differently,
أنهم يحاولون ان يجعلوا حياتهم مختلفة،
and worldwide, we've got communities across America
وفي جميع أنحاء العالم، ولدينا مجتمعات في أنحاء أمريكا
and Japan -- it's incredible, isn't it? I mean,
واليابان--أنه أمر لا يصدق، أليس كذلك؟ أعني
America and Japan and New Zealand.
أمريكا واليابان ونيوزيلندا.
People after the earthquake in New Zealand visited us
بعد الزلزال الذي حصل في نيوزيلندا قاموا بزيارتنا
in order to incorporate some of this public spiritedness
لكي يقومو بدمج وتوحيد روح الشعب
around local growing into the heart of Christchurch.
حول فكرة الزراعة المحلية في قلب مدينة كرايست شيرش.
And none of this takes more money
ولا شيء من هذ يتطلب اي من المال
and none of this demands a bureaucracy,
ولا شيء من هذا يتطلب جــــــهــــاز بـــيــــروقــــــــــراطــــــــي،
but it does demand that you think things differently
ولكن ذلك يتطلب أن تفكر بالأمور بطريقة مختلفة
and you are prepared to bend budgets and work programs
والإستعداد للتطوع والمساهمة المالية
in order to create that supportive framework
من أجل إنشاء هذا الهيكل الداعم
that communities can bounce off.
الذي يساعد المجتمع تكوين أفكاره الجديدة.
And there's some great ideas already in our patch.
وهناك بعض الأفكار العظيمة التي لدينا.
Our local authority has decided to make everywhere
قررت حكومتنا المحلية أن تجعل من كل مكان
Incredible Edible, and in support of that
"شيئا مدهشا يمكن أكله"، وتأييداً لذلك
have decided to do two things.
قررت السلطة المحلية بالقيام بشيئين.
First, they're going to create an asset register of spare land
أولاً، تخصيص الأراض الخالية
that they've got, put it in a food bank so that communities
التي لديهم، ووضعها في بنك الطعام بحيث يقوم المجتمع
can use that wherever they live,
باستعمالها خلال حياتهم،
and they're going to underpin that with a license.
وسيدعمون ذلك بترخيص.
And then they've said to every single one of their workforce,
وسيقولون لكل شخص من قواهم العاملة،
if you can, help those communities grow,
إذا كنت تستطيع، ساعد هذه المجتمعات على النمو،
and help them to maintain their spaces.
وساعدهم في الحفاظ على مساحاتهم.
Suddenly, we're seeing actions on the ground
فجأة، رأينا تأثير هذا على الأرض
from local government. We're seeing this mainstreamed.
من الحكومة المحلية. نحن نشاهد هذا يصبح ظاهرة.
We are responding creatively at last to what Rio demanded
نحن في النهاية نستجيب الى ما طلبه منا "اجتماع "رايو" للبيئة'
of us, and there's lots more you could do.
، وهناك الكثير من الذي بأمكاننا ان نفعله.
I mean, just to list a few. One, please stop putting
أعني، دعوني أذكر بعضها. واحد، يرجى التوقف عن وضع
prickly plants around public buildings. It's a waste of space.
النبات الشائكة حول المباني العامة. أنها مضيعة للمكان.
(Laughter) Secondly, please create -- please, please create
(ضحك) ثانيا، أرجوكم أنشئوا -- رجاء، رجاء أنشؤوا
edible landscapes so that our children start to walk
المناظر الطبيعية الصالحة للأكل بحيث يصبح أولادنا يحبون المشي
past their food day in, day out, on our high streets,
يمضون يومهم بقرب الطعام كل يوم، في شوارعنا،
in our parks, wherever that might be.
في حدائقنا، في أي مكان.
Inspire local planners to put the food sites at the heart
الهموا المخططين المحليين لوضع مواقع الغذاء في وسط
of the town and the city plan, not relegate them
المدينة و في خطة المدينة، لا أن يقصوها
to the edges of the settlements that nobody can see.
إلى حافة المستوطنات التي لا أحد يستطيع أن يراها.
Encourage all our schools to take this seriously.
يجب ان نحث جميع المدارس بأن تأخذ هذا بمحمل الجد.
This isn't a second class exercise.
هذه ليست عملية للدرجة ثانية.
If we want to inspire the farmers of tomorrow,
إذا كنا نريد أن نلهم المزارعين في المستقبل،
then please let us say to every school,
رجاء دعونا نقول لكل مدرسة،
create a sense of purpose around the importance
أن تخلق احساسا ساميا حول أهمية
to the environment, local food and soils.
البيئة، والأغذية المحلية والتربة.
Put that at the heart of your school culture,
ضع ذلك في قلب حضارة المدرسة،
and you will create a different generation.
وسوف تقوم بإنشاء جيل مختلف.
There are so many things you can do, but ultimately
وهناك الكثير من الأشياء التي يمكنك القيام بها، ولكن في نهاية المطاف
this is about something really simple.
كل هذا يتعلق بشيء بسيط جداً.
Through an organic process, through
من خلال عملية عضوية، من خلال
an increasing recognition of the power of small actions,
تزايد التصديق بقوة الأعمال الصغيرة،
we are starting, at last, to believe in ourselves again,
أننا بدأنا، أخيرا، نؤمن بأنفسنا مرة أخرى،
and to believe in our capacity, each and every one of us,
ونؤمن بقدرتنا، كل واحد منا،
to build a different and a kinder future,
لبناء مستقبل مختلف ومنوع،
and in my book, that's incredible.
وفي كتابي، هذا الامر لا يصدق.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا. (تصفيق)